Inventory of the Margaret E. Hill Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Margaret E. Hill papers
1940-1949
79071
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes, 9 envelopes, 3 phonorecords (5.5 linear feet)
Press releases, bulletins, correspondence, pamphlets, clippings, brochures, photographs, motion picture film, and phonorecords, relating to fundraising in southern California for World War II relief activities. Sound use copies of sound recordings available.
Hill, Margaret E.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1979.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Margaret E. Hill graduated from Mills College in 1922 and received advanced degrees from Western Reserve University and the University of Grenoble. In 1935 she moved to Los Angeles to teach French at the Marlborough School. From 1942 to 1947 she held positions in relief organizations in the Los Angeles area, serving as the southern California chairman of American Relief for France, executive secretary of the United Nations War Relief Council for Southern California, and vice-chairman of the Los Angeles County War Chest. To commemorate her relief work, Hill was decorated by the French government with the Legion of Honor in 1947. After the United Nations War Relief Council was dissolved in December 1947, Hill resumed her teaching career at the Anoakia School for Girls in Arcadia, California. She retired in 1967.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Margaret E. Hill papers document her years working for World War II relief organizations in southern California. The papers consist of press releases, bulletins, correspondence, pamphlets, clippings, brochures, photographs, motion picture film, and phonorecords.
As chair of American Relief for France in Southern California, Hill was primarily responsible for fundraising. Her projects for the organization, including the city of Los Angeles's adoption of Calais and Argentan, are documented in the American Relief for France file. She also led a program to send packages to French orphans after the war; files about this initiative include dossiers, lists, and photographs of the children served. In gratitude, the city of Calais sent Hill albums of photographs and children's drawings, all of which can be found in the Oversize material file.
In July 1942 Hill represented French relief at the inaugural meeting of the United Nations War Relief Council (UNWRC). The Council was incorporated in California to coordinate the activities of relief agencies for China, Czechoslovakia, France, Greece, Holland, Norway, the Philippines, and Poland. After being appointed executive secretary in 1943, Hill ran a fundraising campaign that included radio programs publicizing relief efforts, transcripts and recordings of which are included in the United Nations War Relief Council and Sound recordings files.
As a coordinator of relief efforts throughout southern California, Hill collected and received Photographs, Films, and Printed Matter produced by other World War II relief agencies.
United Nations. War Relief Council for Southern California..; International relief.; World War, 1939-1945--California.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.
- American Relief for France file, 1943-1949 (Box 1-2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains correspondence, clippings, photographs, reports, lists, exhibit materials, and printed matter. Around 1946, the organization changed its name to American Aid to France, which may be found on some of the later documents.
  Arrangement note
  In alphabetical order by project or form and thereunder chronologically
  - Argentan file, 1948 (Folder 1: 1-2)
  - Calais file, 1946-1947
    - Le siège de Calais et le dévouement des six bourgeois, by Maurice Martin, Calais city archivist, circa 1946 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Report by American Aid to France transport driver J.A. Manley, circa 1946 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Aperçu de l'histoire de Calais, 1947 January 3 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Florence Gilliam letter on conditions in Calais, 1947 March 31 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Package adoption program files, 1944-1949
    - Red Cross Prisoner of War package guidelines, 1944 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Package adoption program proposal, 1945 November (Folder 1: 8)
    - Index cards, 1945-1946 (Folder 1: 9)
      Cards include names of children, age, status of parents, and photographs
    - List of children, 1946 March (Folder 1: 10)
    - Los Angeles Times clipping, 1946 May 26 (Folder 1: 11)
      Article includes a photograph of Hill
    - Thank you letters from France, 1946-1948 (Folder 1: 12)
    - Fundraising appeal, 1949 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Public relations bureau file, 1944-1948
    - Promotional materials, 1946-1947
      - 1,200,000 Thanks for 1,200,000 Chocolate Bars, 1946 (Folder 1: 14)
      - Le Théatre de la mode: A Creation by French Artists and Designers Organised by the Chambre Syndicale de la Couture Parisienne; Presented to New York by American Relief for France under the Auspices of l'Association Française d'Action Artistique in Aid of l'Entr'Aide française, 1946 (Folder 1: 15)
    - Reports, 1944-1948 (Folder 1: 16-17)
      Includes reports on Grand-Synthe and joint activities between American Relief for France and the American Friends Service Committee
  - Exhibit material on the war in France, produced by the Coordinating Council of French Relief Societies, 1943 (Folder 2: 1-5)
    Includes reprints of photographs by Thérèse Bonney
- United Nations War Relief Council file, 1943-1947 (Box 3)
  Contains bulletins, clippings, correspondence, flyers, minutes, radio transcripts, and reports
  In alphabetical order by form or title and thereunder chronologically
  - Correspondence, 1944-1947
    - California War Chest, 1944-1945 (Folder 3: 1)
    - Carnet, Joseph M., 1944 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Coordinating Council of French Relief Societies, 1944 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Royal Norwegian Information Service, 1944 and 1947 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Sayler, Lucie R., 1946 (Folder 3: 5)
    - United Yugoslav Relief Fund of America, 1944 (Folder 3: 6)
    - Wooster, John B., circa 1945 (Folder 3: 7)
      On the Philippines
  - Clippings on fundraising events, 1943-1947 (Folder 3: 8-10)
  - Bulletins, 1944 (Folder 3: 11)
  - Flyers and clippings advertising poster exhibit, 1944 April (Folder 3: 12)
  - "History of the United Nations War Relief Council,", 1947 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Letterhead, War Relief Councils, 1945-1947 (Folder 3: 14)
  - Meeting minutes, 1947 December 3 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Radio broadcast transcripts, 1944-1947
    - Françoise Dony interview on the German occupation of Belgium, 1944 (Folder 3: 16)
    - Irena Grodzka interview, 1944 July 19 (Folder 3: 17)
      Grodzka was a captain of the Women's Auxiliary Service (WAS) in Poland (Pomocnicza Służba Kobiet or PSK)
    - One minute radio spots to raise money for relief efforts in Czechoslovakia, Poland, Holland, and France, circa 1946 (Folder 3: 18)
    - Claude Angles interview on the French underground, circa 1946 (Folder 3: 19)
    - Jean-Pierre Aumont and Stanley Maw interview on French relief, circa 1946 (Folder 3: 20)
    - Radio program by Ralph Rose featuring Basil Rathbone, Jean Hersholt, and Anna Mae Wong, circa 1946 (Folder 3: 21)
    - "Your World Tomorrow," program with Donald M. Nelson, President of the Society of Independent Motion Picture Producers and Chairman of the United Nations War Relief Council, Warren A. Wilson, and Manchester Boddy, publisher of the Los Angeles Daily News., circa 1946 (Folder 3: 22)
    - "Down in Flames, Out by Underground," by Bierne Lay, adapted by Leona Wilson, 1947 June 6 (Folder 3: 23)
    - "This Day Remembered,", 1947 June 6 (Folder 3: 24)
      See also Sound recordings
    - Charles Boyer, Jean Sablon, Louis Jourdan, and Alexandre de Manziarly interviews, 1947 June 18 (Folder 3: 25)
  - Reports on Great Britain and Holland Relief, 1943-1947 (Folder 3: 26)
- Printed matter, 1941-1946 (Box 3-4)
  Contains pamphlets, brochures, and flyers
  In alphabetical order by issuing organization
  - America Denmark Relief, 1943 (Folder 3: 27)
  - American Aid to France, 1942-1946 (Folder 3: 28)
  - American Committee for Luxembourg Relief, 1943 (Folder 3: 29)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1942-1944 (Folder 3: 30)
  - American Red Cross, 1943-1944 (Folder 3: 31-32)
    Includes Prisoners of War Bulletin
  - American Relief for Czechoslovakia, 1946 (Box 3: 33)
  - American Relief for Holland, 1946 (Folder 3: 34)
  - American Relief for Norway, 1942-1944 (Folder 3: 35)
  - American Relief for Poland, 1946 (Folder 3: 36)
  - American Society for Russian Relief, 1946 (Folder 3: 37)
  - Belgian Information Center, 1941-1943 (Folder 3: 38)
  - Belgian War Relief Society, 1941-1943 (Folder 3: 39)
  - British War Relief Society, 1943-1945 (Folder 4: 1)
  - California War Chest, 1945 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Czechoslovak National Council of America, 1942-1943 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Fighting French Relief Committee, 1942-1944 (Folder 4: 4)
  - French Press and Information Service, 1944 and 1946 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Greek Office of Information, circa 1943 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Greek War Relief Association, 1943 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Help the Children Committee, 1943 (Folder 4: 8)
  - Los Angeles Area War Chest, 1943 (Folder 4: 9)
  - Los Angeles Committee for Christian Refugee Relief, 1942 (Folder 4: 10)
  - National Congress of Industrial Organizations War Relief Committee, 1944 (Folder 4: 11)
  - National Committee on Food, 1943 (Folder 4: 12)
  - National War Fund, 1943 (Folder 4: 13)
  - Netherlands Information Bureau, 1943 (Folder 4: 14)
  - Polish Government Information Center, 1945-1946 (Folder 4: 15)
  - Polish War Relief, 1943-1945 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Queen Wilhemina Fund, 1942-1943 (Folder 4: 17)
  - Refugee Relief Trustees, 1943 (Folder 4: 18)
  - Russian War Relief, 1944 (Folder 4: 19)
  - Le Secours Français, 1944 (Folder 4: 20)
  - Unitarian Service Committee, 1943 (Folder 4: 21)
  - United China Relief, 1943-1946 (Folder 4: 22-23)
  - United Czechoslovak Relief, 1943 (Folder 4: 24)
  - United Jewish Appeal, 1943 (Folder 4: 25)
  - United Seaman's Service, 1943 (Folder 4: 26)
  - United Service Organizations, 1942-1944 (Folder 4: 27)
  - United Service to Holland, 1946 (Folder 4: 28)
  - United States Committee for the Care of European Children, 1943 (Folder 4: 29)
  - United Yugoslav Relief Fund, 1943 (Folder 4: 30)
  - War Prisoners Aid of the Young Men's Christian Associations, 1943-1944 (Folder 4: 31)
  - Yiddish Scientific Institute, 1944 (Folder 4: 32)
- Oversize material, 1944-1947 (Box 5)
  Contains a poster and albums of photographs and drawings
  Arranged chronologically
  - City of Calais album dedicated to American Aid to France, 1946 (Box 6)
    Contains watercolor and crayon drawings by children
  - City of Calais album dedicated to Los Angeles, 1946 (Box 7)
    Contains photographs of buildings in Calais after the war
  - Federation of Religious Vacation Camps album presented to American Aid to France, 1946 December (Box 7)
    Contains photographs of children in Calais
  - Christmas poster dedicated to American Aid to France from the city of Calais, 1947 December (Box 5)
  - Artworks and postcards of France, undated (Box 6)
- Films, 1940s (Box 5 and Film shelf)
  Except for one 25mm film strip, all are 16mm acetate film reels.
  In alphabetical order by canister title
  - "8.L.0.2" (Folder Film shelf)
  - "Belgium" (Folder Film shelf)
  - "Bridge to Yinhsi" (Folder Film shelf)
  - "Corsica" (Folder Film shelf)
  - "Let's Look at China," United China Relief, 1944 (Box 5)
    150 still pictures of China on 25mm film strip
- Photographs, 1940-1947 (Box Photo file)
  Contains prints and negatives from press services and relief agencies
  - Calais, France, after World War II, 1946-1947 (Folder A)
    Large format negatives
  - "Le Théatre de la mode" exhibit, 1946 (Folder B)
    Photographs from an exhibit featuring the work of French artists and designers organized by American Relief for France. See Box 1 for exhibit catalog
  - Calais, France, after World War II, 1946-1947 (Folder C)
    Includes index of photographs
  - United Nations War Relief Council fundraising events in Los Angeles, 1945-1947 (Folder D)
    Includes photograph of Pearl S. Buck
  - American Relief for France in Calais, 1942-1947 (Folder E)
  - Norwegian Official Photo Service, 1940-1943 (Folder F)
    Depicts bombing in Narvik, Norway and conditions during the German occupation
  - American Relief for Czechoslovakia photo service, 1944-1947 (Folder G)
    Includes the Czechoslovak army training in England and Edvard Beneš with soldiers
  - Polish Government Information Center photo service, 1943-1944 (Folder H)
    Depicts victims in Warsaw, Polish refugees in Iran, and the concentration camp Majdanek
  - Miscellaneous relief agencies, 1942-1946 (Folder I)
    Contains photographs from British War Relief, Russian War Relief, United China Relief, United Yugoslav Relief, and War Prisoners Aid
- Sound recordings, 1944 and 1947 (Box Record cabinet)
  Contains broadcast recordings produced by United China Relief and the UNWRC
  In alphabetical order by disc title
  - "Let's Look at China," United China Relief, 1944
    16" vinyl disc
  - "A Message from France," with Jean-Pierre Aumont, circa 1946 (Folder Record cabinet)
    12" vinyl disc
  - "This Day Remembered", 1947 June 6 (Folder Record cabinet)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Use copy reference number: 79071_a_0002897
    Radio dramatization commemorating the third anniversary of D-Day. Describes American pilots shot down, rescued by a French farmer, and aided by the French underground. Use copy available on computer workstation
  - "United Nations War Relief Council,", 1947 June (Folder Record cabinet)
    Side A: "Sale of America." Side B: One minute cuts on the UN, Holland, Norway, Poland, Philippines, France. 16" vinyl disc